<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The knowledge of things vnkowne Apperteyning to astronomy, wyth necessary rules, and certayne speares contayned in the same. Compyled by Godfridus super palladium de agricultura  Anglicatum.</title>
            <title>This booke of astronomye</title>
            <author>Godfridus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1585</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01797</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11932</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121577</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856756</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856756</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22380</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01797)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22380)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 888:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The knowledge of things vnkowne Apperteyning to astronomy, wyth necessary rules, and certayne speares contayned in the same. Compyled by Godfridus super palladium de agricultura  Anglicatum.</title>
                  <title>This booke of astronomye</title>
                  <author>Godfridus.</author>
                  <author>Palladius, Rutilius Taurus Aemilianus. De re rustica.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[112] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Fleetestreete, beneath the Conduit, at the signe of S. Iohn Euangelist, by H. Iackson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1585.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An edition, with additions, of: This booke of astronomye.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The booke of knowledge.</note>
                  <note>"The additions include sections on bones, veins, and a rutter of distances between ports."--STC.</note>
                  <note>Connection with the "De re rustica" of Palladius is unclear, as are Godfridus's identity and the early history of this text.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Knowledge of Thinges <hi>vnknowne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Apperteyning to Aſtronomy, wyth neceſſary Rules, and certayne Speares contayned in the ſame.</p>
            <p>Compyled by Godfridus ſuper palladium de agricultura Anglicatum.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London, in</hi> Fleeteſtreete, beneath the Conduite, at the Signe of S Iohn Euangeliſt, by H. Iackſon. 1585.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Ptholomeus.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>¶ This is vnknown to many men, though they be knowne to ſome men.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:2"/>
            <head>¶ Here beginneth the Booke of Knowledge.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Sunday.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the Natiuitye of oure Lord come on a Sunday winter ſhall be good, Ver ſhalbe windy, ſweete and hoate, Vintage ſhall be good, Oxen waxeth, ſhepe ſhalbe mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied, Hony and milke, and all goods ſhalbe plenteous. Olde men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhall dye, peace and accord ſhalbe in the land. Alſo the Sundayes of ech yeare in the hower of the day, or of night, to doe all thinges that thou wilt begin it is profitable. Who that bene born ſhalbe ſtrong great and ſhining. Who that flieth ſhalbe found.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Monday.</head>
               <p>If it come on the Monday, Wynter ſhall bee medled. Verre ſhall bee windye and good, Sommer all
<pb facs="tcp:22380:3"/>drye or euen the contrarye, if it be ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny &amp; full of tempeſt, Vintage ſhal be in middle aſſiſe. In ech Mondaye of the ſame yere, in the hower of day, or of night, to doe all thinges that thou wilt begin it is good, dreames pertayneth to effecte. Who that is borne ſhall be ſtrong. Who that flyeth ſhall ſoone be found, thefte done ſhalbe proued. He that falleth into his bed, ſoone ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Tueſday.</head>
               <p>IF it come on the Tueſday, winter ſhall be good. Ver ſhalbe wyndie, Sommer ſhall be good, Vintage ſhal he trauaylous, women ſhall dye, ſhips ſhall periſhe on Seas. In each Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day of the ſame yeare, in the hower of day or of night, to doe all thinges that thou wilte begin it is good. Who that is borne ſhall be ſtrong and couetous, dreames pertayneth to age. Who that flyeth ſhall ſoone be found, thefte than
<pb facs="tcp:22380:3"/>done ſhalbe proued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Wedneſday.</head>
               <p>IF it come on the Wedneſday, wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall be ſharpe and harde. Ver ſhall be wyndye and euell, Sommer ſhall be good. Vintage ſhall be good and traueilous, good witte thou ſhalte fynde, yong men ſhall dye, honey ſhall not be earnde, Berers ſhal trauayle, Shipmen ſhall trauaile in eche yeare. In eche Wedneſday of eche yeare, to doe all thinges that thou wilte begin it is good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Thurſday.</head>
               <p>IF it come on the Thurſday, Wynter ſhall bee good. Verre ſhall bee wyndye, Sommer good, Vintage good and plenty ſhall bee Kinges and Princes perameter ſhall dye. And in each Thurſdaye of eche yeare, to doe all thinges that thou wilte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin is good. Who that bene boane
<pb facs="tcp:22380:4"/>ſhallbe of fayre ſpeech and worſhipful. Who flyeth ſhal ſoone be found, thefte done by a wench ſhall be proued. Who that falleth in his bed rather other lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ofte was wont to recouer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Fryday.</head>
               <p>IF it come on the Fryday winter ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be merueilous.</p>
               <p>Ver windy and good, Sommer good and drye, Vintage plenteous, there ſhall be dolour of the ayre, Sheepe, and Been ſhall periſhe. Otes ſhall be deare. In ech Fryday of ech yeare, to doe all thinges that thou wilte begin, it is good. Who that bene borne ſhall be profytable and Lech<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rous. Who that flyeth ſhall ſoone be found, thefte done by a Childe ſhalbe proued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Saturday.</head>
               <p>IF it come on the Saturdaye, Wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall be dyrke, Snowe ſhall bee
<pb facs="tcp:22380:4"/>great, fruite ſhall be plenteous, Ver ſhall be wyndye, Sommer euel. Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage euill by places, Otes ſhalbe dere, men ſhall waxe ſicke, and beene ſhall dye. In no Saterdaye of that ſame yeare, whether it be in the hower of day or night, to begin euery thing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath it ſhall be good, but if the courſe of the moone bring it thereto, thefte done ſhall be founde, hee that flyeth ſhall turne againe to his owne, they that is ſicke ſhall long wayle, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath they ſhall eſcape, that they ne ſhould dye.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ Here followeth of the byrth of Children.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N the Sondaye, who that is borne, hee ſhall bee greate and ſhyning. Who that is borne on the Monday, to begin all
<pb facs="tcp:22380:5"/>thinges he ſhalbe good, who that is borne on the Tueſday, he ſhall be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous, and he ſhall periſh wyth yron, and vnneath he ſhall come to the laſte age, to begin all thinges he ſhall bee good. He that is borne on the Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday, he ſhall lightly learne wordes. He that is borne on the Thurſdaye, he ſhalbe ſtable and worſhipfull, and to begin all thinges is good.</p>
            <p>He that is borne on the Frydaye, hee ſhall be of long lyfe and lecherous, and to begin all thinges it is good. He that is borne on the Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, he ſhal ſeldom be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, but if the courſe of the moone bring it thereto.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:5"/>
            <head>¶ Here beginneth the nature and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the dayes of the moone, with the birth of Children.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The firſt day.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>IN the fyrſt daye of the Moone, Adam was made to doe all thinges it is profytable, &amp; what euer thou wilt to doe good, and that thou ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in thy ſleepe, ſhall be well and ſhall be turned into ioye. If thou ſeemeſte to be ouercommen, neuer the latter, thou ſhalte ouercome. A chylde that is borne ſhall ſoone waxe, and bee of long lyfe, and ritche. He that falleth ſycke ſhall long wayle, and hee ſhall ſuffer a long ſyckneſſe, it is good to let a little blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:22380:6"/>
               <head>The ſeconde day.</head>
               <p>JN the ſecond day of the moone. Eue was made, to do an erand it is good and to doe all thinges it is profitable, to buy and to ſel, and to flye into a ſhip to make away, to ſowe ſeedes, thefte done ſhal ſoone be found. Whatſoeuer thou ſhalt ſee in ſleepe, ſoone effecte it ſhal haue, whether it be good or euel, to let blood it is good. A childe that is borne ſoone ſhall waxe, and he ſhall be a lecherour or a ſtrumper.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ The iii. day.</head>
               <p>IN the third day of the Moone, Cayn was borne, of all thinges that ſhould be done, it behooueth thee to abſtayne, but only that thou wilt not that it wax agayne, it is good to drawe up rootes in the yard, and in the field, theft done ſhall ſoone be found, whatſoeuer thou ſeeſt in ſleepe it is nought, who that is borne menlyche ſhal waxe, but he ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:22380:6"/>dye yong. A ſick man that faleth in his bed ſhal trauayle, and he ſhall not eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape, to let blood it is good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ The iiii. day.</head>
               <p>IN the fourth day of the moone Abel was borne. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hatſoeuer thou doſte is good in eche trauayle. The dreames that thou ſeeſt hath effect, hope in God &amp; counſayle good. A child that is born he ſhalbee a good creature, and much he ſhalbe prayſed. A man that falleth ſicke, eyther ſoone ſhall be healed, or ſoone ſhal dye, it is good to let blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ The .v. day.</head>
               <p>IN the fyfte daye of the Moone, doe nothing of errandene of worke, to make ſacramente, it is not good. Who that flyeth, bounde or dead he ſhal be ſhewed, the dreame that thou ſhalte ſee, ſhall be well. After that thou hath ſeene, it ſhall be. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware
<pb facs="tcp:22380:7"/>ware that thou leeſe no counſayle. A chylde that is borne ſhall dye yong. He that falleth in his bed ſoone ſhall dye, to let blood it is good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ The .vi. day.</head>
               <p>IN the vi. day of the Moone, to ſend children to ſchole it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> good, and to vſe hunting, the dreames y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou ſhalte ſee, ſhall not hap in good, but beware that thou ſay naught to any man. Thy counſayle doe not diſcouer. A chylde borne ſhal be of long lyfe and ſyckly. A ſycke man vnneath ſhall eſcape, to let blood it is good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ The vii. day.</head>
               <p>IN the vii. day of the Moone, A bell was ſlayne. He that falleth ſicke ſhal dye, he that is borne ſhal be of long life and good to lette blood, and to take drinke it is good. A dreame that thou ſeeſt, long after ſhall be. Who that fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſhal ſoone be found, and theft alſo.
<pb facs="tcp:22380:7"/>To buy ſooyne, to tame beaſtes, to clip heires, and to take all manner of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, it is good. A ſicke man if he be medicined ſhall be healed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ The viii. day.</head>
               <p>AND in the viii. day of the Moone, whatſoeuer thou wilt doe is good, all thinges that thou wilt treate, to go in counſayle, to buy Manciples, and beaſtes, foldes of ſheepe into an other place, to change it is good, to ſet foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentes, to ſo we ſeedes, to go in a way. A childe that is borne ſhalbe ſick, but in al dayes he ſhalbe a purchaſour, and he ſhall dye yong. A dreame ſhall be certaine, and ſoone ſhall bee. If thou ſeeſt ſorry thinges, turne then to the eaſt, he that waxeth ſick ſhall lyue, thefte ſhalbe found, to let blood it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth in the middeſt of the day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ The ix. day.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:22380:8"/>
               <p>ANd in the ninth day of the Moone Lameth was borne, to doe all thinges it is profytable, what thing thou wilt enter to make, it is good, and ſhall profyte. A dreame that thou ſeeſt ſhall come in the daye following, or in the ſeconde day, and thou ſhalte ſee a ſygne in the Eaſt, and that ſhall apere in ſlepe openly, within xi. dayes ſhall come, a child borne in all thinges, ſhalbe a purchaſour and good, &amp; long of life. A ſicke man ſhall waile much, &amp; ariſe. Who ſhalbe chaſed ſhall not bee found, &amp; who that is oppreſſed ſhalbee comforted, preſume thou not to let blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ The x. day.</head>
               <p>ANd in the tenth daye of the Moone was borne the Patriarke Noe. Whatſoeuer thou wilte doe, ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to lighte, Dreames be in dayne, and within iiii. dayes ſhall come wyth out perrill, a childe that is borne ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:22380:8"/>enuyron many countries, and he ſhall dye olde, whatſoeuer be loſte ſhall bee hyde, who that is bounde ſhal be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounde. Who that flyeth after, ſhalbee found: Who that falleth in trauayle, without perrill ſhalbe deliuered, who that falleth into his bed, he ſhall long abide, to let blood it is good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ The xi. day.</head>
               <p>AND in the xi. day of the Moone, Sem was borne, it is good to begin workes, to go out to ſeeke, to make wedding. A dreame wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in .iiii. dayes ſhall be fulfylled wyth out perrils, and ſuch it ſhall appeare after that thou ſeeſt. A chylde that is borne ſhall bee of long lyfe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, and loueable, he ſhall haue a ſygne in the forehead, or in the mouth, or in the eye, and in latter age he ſhalbe made better. A wenche ſhall haue a
<pb facs="tcp:22380:9"/>ſygne that ſhee ſhall bee learned wyth wiſdome, to goe into a way, it is good and to chaunge foldes of ſheepe from place to place, he that is ſyck, and he be long ſycke, he ſhalbe healed, ech day to let blood it is good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ The xii. day.</head>
               <p>AND in the xii. day of the Moone, was borne Canaan the ſonne of Cham, nothing thou ſhalte begin, for it is a greenous daye, a dreame ſhall be certayne, to ioye to thee after that thou ſeeſt within ix. dayes, it ſhall be fulfylled. To wed and to doe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rands it is profytable, that is loſt ſhall be found. A child that is borne ſhalbe of long lyfe, angry, and honeſt, a ſicke man ſhallbe greeued and aryſe, who that is taken ſhalbe lefte, thefte ſoone ſhall be found, to let blood at euen it is good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:22380:9"/>
               <head>The xiii. day.</head>
               <p>ANd in the thirteene daye of the Moone, Noe planted Vynes, and in eache daye Vynes beene made, to plante Vines it is good, after that thou ſeeſt, thy dreame ſhalbe, and with in foure dayes, it ſhall come to glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but take heede to Pſalmes, and to Dryſons. A chylde borne in aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie ſhalbe let, he ſhall bee angry, and he ſhall not be long of lyfe. Who that is bound ſhall be looſed, that is loſte ſhall be found. Who that waxeth ſicke long time ſhall trauayle, and vnneath ſhalbe ſaued but dye. To wed a wyfe, it is good. It is good eche daye to let blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The xiiii. day.</head>
               <p>THe xiiii. daye of the Moone, is a good daye and a glade. Noe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all thinges that ſhalbe done, what ſoeuer thou wilte doe, and ſhall come to thee to heale. A dreame within ſixe
<pb facs="tcp:22380:10"/>dayes ſhall be, to make wedding it is good, and to goe in the waye. Axe of thy friend, or thine enemye, and it ſhall be done to thee. A chylde that is borne, ſhall be a traytour, the ſicke man ſhall be chaunged and ryſe, and ſhalbe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by medicine, to let blood it is good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ The xv. day.</head>
               <p>ANd in the xv. daye of the Moone, Tongues were deuided, doe no worke, begin no erand, for it is a gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous day. A ſicke man ſhall long tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle, but hee ſhall eſcape. A dreame that thou ſeeſt nothing ſhall noy, but ſoone ſhall come. A chylde borne ſhall dye yong, that is loſt ſhall be founde, to let blood it is good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ The xvi. day.</head>
               <p>ANd in the xvi. daye of the Moone Pythagoras was borne, the au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thour of Phyloſophers, to buy and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22380:10"/>ſell it is good, to tame Oxen and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Beaſtes. A dreame is not good after long time it ſhall come, and it ſhalbe harmefull, to take a wife and to make wedding it is good, foldes of ſheepe from place to place to chaunge it is good. A chyld that is borne ſhalbe of long lyfe, but he ſhalbe poore, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworne and accuſed. A ſicke man if he chaunge his place, he ſhall liue, to let blood it is good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The xvii. day.</head>
               <p>IN the xvii. daye of the Moone, it is euill to doe an erand, a dreame that thou ſeeſt, after long time ſhalbe, or within xxx. dayes. A Childe that is borne ſhalbe ſely, he that is ſick ſhalbe much greeued and aryſe, that is loſte, ſhalbe found, to ſend children to ſchole, to be wedded, and to make medicine, and to take it, is good, but not to lette blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The xviii. day.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:22380:11"/>
               <p>AND in the xviii. daye of the Moone, is good for all thinges to be done, namely to begyn houſes. And to ſet children to ſchoole, dreames are good, and ſhalbe done wythin xx. dayes. Who that ſickneſſe hath, ſhall ſoone riſe or long be ſicke, and then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer, thefte then done ſhall bee found. A knaue childe then borne ſhall be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouercome and eloquente, prowde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaceable, &amp; not long lyfe. A maid child than borne, ſhalbe chaſte, laborous, ſenyaunte, and better in her hynder age, they ſhall both be marked aboue the knees, not ſo hardye thou to lette blood this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The xix. day.</head>
               <p>IN the xix. daye of the Moone, is not full good, ne full euill, dreames ſhall come within xx. dayes, who that hath ſickneſſe ſhall ſoone ryſe, if bee take medicine, thefte than done, ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:22380:11"/>not be founde: A knaue chylde then borne, ſhalbe true, benynge, fleight, wyſe, euer waxe better and better in great worſhippe, and haue a marke in the brow. A mayde chylde then borne, ſhalbe right ſicke: ſaue not payde of one man, that day is good to bleede.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The .xx. day.</head>
               <p>AND in the Twentye Daye of the Moone, Iſaack bleſſed hys Sonne, what euer thou wilte do is good, a dreame that thou ſeeſt ſhall appeare, but ſay it to no man, to make wedding is good, to buy a manciple, it is good, to builde houſes it is good, to change foldes of ſheeepe from place to place, it is good, and to tame beaſts and to ſo we ſeedes. A chylde that is borne, ſhalbe a fyghter and hee ſhall haue many aryuynges, that is loſte ſhalbe founde, to chaunge beene it is good. A ſycke man ſhall long wayle
<pb facs="tcp:22380:12"/>or ſoone aryſe, to let blood on euen it is good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The .xxi. day.</head>
               <p>ANd in the xxi. daye of the Moone, Saule was borne, fyrſt King of the Iewes, a dreame is true, and to ioye ſhal pertaine within iiii. dayes. A child that is borne ſhall fynde much euill, he ſhalbe a theefe, and witty, he ſhall be a traytor, and traueilous, Eſau toke the reſidue bleſſing of his father, it is good to heale ſwyne, and other beaſtes, it behoueth to abſtaine from gamyng thinges, to goe in the way it is good. A ſicke man ſhalbe ſick and aryſe, thefte ſhalbe found, let no blood neyther day nor night.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The xxii. day.</head>
               <p>IN the xxii. daye of the Moone Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph was borne, it is a daye of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſſe, if thou doeſt any errand, thou ſhalt fynd it greeuous, dreames ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:22380:12"/>certayne and ſhall come to ioy. A child borne in all days, ſhalbe a purchaſour, merry, faire, religious, and leperous. A ſicke man both late is confyrmed, and healed. Beene to chaunge from place to place it is good. A ſick man ſhall be ſicke and be healed, to let blood all day is good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The xxiii. day.</head>
               <p>IN the xxiii. day of the Moone, Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iamin was borne, Sonne of the right ſyde, the laſte ſonne of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarke Noe. What euer thou wilte do is good. A dreame that thou ſeeſt, ſhall turne to ioy, and nothinge ſhall noye, and other while it was wonte to fall within eyghte dayes. To take a wyfe it is good, to make wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges, to ſet foundamentes, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen newe earth, to tame Beaſtes, it is good. A chylde borne, ſhall be out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt, and many lettinges, hee ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:22380:13"/>make, and in ſynnes he ſhall dye.</p>
               <p>A ſicke man ſhall be ſicke, and ariſe, it is good to let blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The xxiiii. day.</head>
               <p>IN the xxiiii. daye of the Moone Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyas was borne, a dreame that thou ſeeſt ſignifyeth thy heale, and nothing ſhall noye, a childe borne ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious, and ſhall doe wonderfull thinges. A ſicke man ſhall languiſhe and be healed, to let blood before the thirde hower it is good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The xxv. day.</head>
               <p>In the xxv. daye of the Moone, our Lorde ſente ſygnes into Egipte by Moyſes, and in eche day he paſſed the red ſea, he that maketh ſacramente, ſhall dye in a perrillous death, beware dread to come, the dreame ſignifyeth harde things, and within x. dayes it was wonte to come. Early then bowe thine heade into the Eaſte. A chylde
<pb facs="tcp:22380:13"/>borne ſhalbe an euill man, many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilles he ſhall ſuffer. A ſycke man ſhall ſuſtaine iniurye, and vnneath ſhall eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape, it is good to let blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The xxvi. day.</head>
               <p>IN the xxvi. day of the Moone Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes dryed the red Sea. In the daye Ionathas the ſonne of Saule was borne, &amp; dead is Saule wyth his ſons, thou ſhalte begin nothing, the dreame ſhalbe certayne, and ſhalbe turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ioye, to men Pilgrimes it pertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to beware of ſpyes, of thyne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. A chylde borne ſhall be full loueable, but neyther ritche nor pore. A ſycke man ſhall trauayle and aryſe, it he haue the Dropſye, he ſhall dye, to let blood a little it is needefull.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The xxvii. day.</head>
               <p>IN the xxvii. Daye of the Moone, oure Lorde rayned Manna, to
<pb facs="tcp:22380:14"/>the children of Iſrael, what euer thou wilte do is good, be buſy, for a dreame that thou ſeeſt was wont to come, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to good or euill. A chylde borne ſhalbe of long lyfe, and moſte loued. and menelyche ſtraunge, neither riche nor pore. A ſycke man ſhall riſe to life, he ſhall be holden in much langoure, but he ſhall be healed, foldes of ſheepe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> place to place to change it is good, to let blood on euen is good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The xxviii. day.</head>
               <p>ANd in the xxviii. day of the Moone the dayes be fighting Tabernacles bene fixed in Deſarte, what euer thou wilte doe is good: a dreame that thou ſeeſt ſhall turne into ioy, and ſhal come welfullich. A child borne ſhalbe muche loued, he ſhalbe holded in ſickneſſe, a ſicke man that faſteth in infyrmitye, ſoone ſhall be ſaued, to let blood in the euening it accordeth.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:14"/>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The xxix. day.</head>
               <p>ANd in the xxix. day of the Moone, the Iewes went into the lande of beheaſt. Herode the King cutte of the childrens heades, begin nothing, the dreame ſhalbe certaine, and good glad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe and ioy it ſignifyeth, an errande begon, it is good to fullfyll, to take a wyfe it is good, but nilte thou not to make dowers, ne wryte Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. A childe borne ſhalbe of long lyfe, wyſe, and holy, and meke, to fiſh, and hunt it is good, a ſicke man ſhall not greeuouſly be ſicke, but ſcape, it is good to let blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The xxx. day.</head>
               <p>ANd in the xxx. Day of the Moone, Samuell the Prophete, was borne, whatſoeuer thou wilte doe is good, a dreame that appeareth to thee certayne, and within ii. dayes
<pb facs="tcp:22380:15"/>thou ſhalte ſee, and thou ſhalte fynde a red ſygne in the Eaſt, within ix. dayes. A chylde borne ſhalbe of long lyfe and profytable, and well meaſured in eche thing. A ſyck man ſhal nigh come to deth, in no ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner let no blud. Theſe and many other pertaineth to men after as the courſe of the moone fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <trailer>¶ Here endeth the nature and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the dayes of the Moone wyth the byrth of Chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>And here follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth of Saturne and what Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne is.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:15"/>
            <p>SAturne, what is Saturne, he is the fyrſte Planet and the wickeddeſte, and he vnbeginneth the Zodyacke but once in thyrtye yeares, than fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth it forth in the Zodyacke by xii. ſygnes, that Saturne reigneth in eche ſygnes ii. yeares &amp; a halfe, in .vi. ſygnes he raigneth xv. yeares. And in all the xii. ſygnes he reigneth euen xxx. yeares, and right as there are twelue ſygnes in the Zodyacke, ſo are there twelue monthes in the yeare, eache ſygne to his month. Wherfore beware before, and make purueyaunce there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and looke when Saturne reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the iii. winter ſygnes, that is to ſay, Capricorne, Aquarie, and Piſces, and ſo long thoſe vii. yeares and halfe a yeare, ſhalbe ſcarſenes and dearth of corne, fruite, Beaſtes, and all other thinges, for in the .iii. yeares ſignes he hath might and moſt power to fulfyll his malice if he be not letted by neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood of any good planet.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:16"/>
            <head>¶ What the Thunder ſignifyeth in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery yeare.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hunder in Ianuary ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfyeth the ſame yeare, great wyndes, plentye of corne, and battaile perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture alſo. Thunder in February, ſygnifyeth that ſame yeare many men, namely rich men, ſhall dye in great ſickneſſe. Thunder in March ſignifyeth that ſame yeare great win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, plentye of cornes, and debate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt people. Thunder in Aprill, ſignifyeth that ſame yeare to be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and merry, and alſo death of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men. Thunder in Maye, ſygnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that yeare, neede, ſcarceneſſe, and dearth of cornes, and greate hunger. Thunder in Iune, ſignifieth that ſame yeare, that woodes ſhalbe ouercaſten with windes, and great raging ſhall be of Lyons, and Wolues, and ſo lyke
<pb facs="tcp:22380:16"/>of other harmefull Beaſtes. Thunder in Iuly, ſignifyeth that ſame yeare ſhalbe good corne, and fruites of Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, that is to ſay, their ſtrength ſhall periſhe. Thunder in Auguſt, ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſame yeare, ſorrowe, wayling of many, and of moſt hote thinges, and alſo many ſhall bee ſicke. Thunder in September, ſignifieth that ſame yere great wynd, copye of corne, that is to ſay plenteous, and occaſyon of folke, that is to ſay, much falling. Thunder in October ſignifyeth the ſame yeare, great winde and ſcantneſſe of cornes, of fruites, and trees. Thunder in No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uember, ſignifyeth that ſame yeare, to be fruitefull, and merry, and cheape corne. Thunder in December ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that ſame yeare, cheape corne, and of wheate, peace and accord among the people.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:17"/>
            <head>¶ This Chapter following declareth what are the euill dayes, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodd en in the yeare. And alſo which be the beſt bleeding dayes in the yeare.</head>
            <p>WYt thou well that in euery month be two euill dayes, one in wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Moone, and another in the wanynge. The Kalenders ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth them, and their howers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly ynough, in the whiche dayes, if anye folke take ſickeneſſe, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne anye newe thinge, it is great grace if euer it fare well, or come to good ende. Alſo there are fyftye Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niculer dayes, that is to ſaye, for the xv. Kalend. of Auguſt, to the Nonas of September, in the whiche dayes it is forbidden by Aſtronomye to all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of folkes, that they let them no blood, ne take no drinkes, &amp; alſo good
<pb facs="tcp:22380:17"/>it is to abſtaine then from women, and they ſhold great leches know and keepe, and teache to other men. For whye all that time reygneth a ſtarre, that is called Caniculacanis in latten, a hound in Engliſh, nowe of this fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſtar Canicula, the foreſaide fyftye daies, are called Caniculer dayes, that is to ſay hore dayes, and byting as a Bytch, for the kinde of the ſtar Cany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula, is boyling and brenning as fyre, and biting as a bytch whelp, that time the heate of the ſunne, and of the ſtar, is ſo dowlcet and violent, that mens bodyes at midnight, ſweates as at midday, and ſwelleth lightly, bloweth and brenneth, and if they then be hurt then be they more ſicke, then at anye other time, and right neerer dead. In thoſe dayes all venemous Serpentes creepeth, flyeth, and gendreth, &amp; ſo they ouerſet hugely the ayre, in ſeeding of their kind, ſo that many men are dead
<pb facs="tcp:22380:18"/>thereby, there agayne all the ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>er, namely thoſe dayes, a fyre is good, nighte and daye, and holeſome. And ſeethe ſuch meates, and take heeds of great violent meates.</p>
            <p>Alſo from the xviii. Kalend of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to the xvii. Kalend of Nouember, looke thou take no colde, for then the powers of man, of earth, &amp; of althings elſe ſetten. And they maye not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> agayne till the evill Kalend. of a plil, wherefore ſuch thinges as thou takeſt within the powers, thaffection y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhalt with hold till they open, truly it ſhould leſſe harme thee to take cold at Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas than then.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ To knowe how a man ſhall keepe himſelfe in health.</head>
            <p>IF thou wilte keepe thee long in helth then holde this rule, that is to ſaye, flye anger, wrath, and enuie, &amp; gyue
<pb facs="tcp:22380:18"/>thee to mirth in meaſure, trauaile ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, ſo that thou ſweate not to muche in the Sommer, and namely the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niculer dayes, flye al manner of ſtrong drinkes, and hote ſpices, brenning meates namely to haue them vſandly. Faſte not to long at morue. Suppe not to late at nighte, eate not haſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, nor eate but little at once, and that that thou eateſt, chew it well, euerye time that thou eateſt, reſt a little rather after, fleepe not thou vnder meale, namely but of theſe iiii. months. That is to ſay, Maye, Iune, Iuly, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. And yet the leſſe that thou ſtepeſt then the better it is: to ſleepe well in the waxing of the night, and be earlye up in the morning, tymelyer the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And, euerye daye beware of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked myſtes, that none enter in thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſting, for thereof commeth great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tilences &amp; great heate. And in greate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>old and in peſtilences eate much gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycke
<pb facs="tcp:22380:19"/>euerye day .ix. Safforne chyues, it will doe thee much good. Eate yn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in winter, eate ynough in Ver, but eate but little in Sommer, looke thy meate be well ſeaſoned in Harueſt beware of fruites, for they are not good, if it be giuen thee for medicine, of all manner of meates, ſodden is the beſt, eate not to many hote ſpices, nor eate but little at once, for better it were to eate .vii. times on the day, then once thy fyll, fleſhe is more nouriſhinge then fyſhe, eate not to muche ſowre meates nor ſalte, for they will make thy bones ſore: looke thy drinke be not to newe, ne to olde, ſweete pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred meates be moſte holeſome. Of al thinges take meaſure, and no more, for in meaſure reſtes Vertue. And that Sayntes did holde them to.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ To knowe what perrillous dayes, come in the chaunge of euery Moone.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the chaunge of euerye Moone be ii. dayes in the which, what thing ſoeuer is begon, late or neuer, it ſhall come to good ende, and the dayes be full perillous for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinges.</p>
            <list>
               <item>In Ianuary, when the Moone is iii. or iiii.</item>
               <item>In February .v. or .vii.</item>
               <item>In March .vi. or .vii.</item>
               <item>In Aprill .v. or .viii.</item>
               <item>In May viii. or. ix,</item>
               <item>In Iune .v. or .xv.</item>
               <item>In Iuly iii. or .xiii.</item>
               <item>In Auguſt .viii. or .xiii.</item>
               <item>In September .viii. or .xiii.</item>
               <item>In October .v. or .xii.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:22380:20"/>
               <item>In Nouember .v. or .ix.</item>
               <item>In December .iii. or .xiii.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Aſtronomers ſayeth, that vi. dayes in the yeare are perilous of death. And therfore they forbid men to be let blood on them, or take any drinkes. That is to ſaye.</p>
            <list>
               <item>The thirde daye of the Moneth of Ianuary.</item>
               <item>The fyrſte daye of the Moneth of Iuly.</item>
               <item>The ſeconde daye of the Moneth of October.</item>
               <item>The laſt daye of the Moneth of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill.</item>
               <item>The firſt day of Auguſt.</item>
               <item>The laſte daye going oute of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember.</item>
            </list>
            <p>¶ Theſe vi. dayes wyth greate dilly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence oughte to be kepte, but namely the latter iii. for all the vaynes are then full. For then whether man or beaſte be knit in then, wythin vii.
<pb facs="tcp:22380:20"/>dayes, or certaynly wythin xiiii. dayes they ſhall dye, And if they take anye drinkes wythin xv. dayes, they ſhall dye. And if they eate any gooſe in theſe iii. dayes wythin xl. dayes they ſhall dye. And if any chylde be borne, in theſe iii. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atter dayes, they ſhall dye a wirked death.</p>
            <p>¶ Aſtronomers, and Aſtrologyers, ſayeth, that in the beginning of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the vii. night d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the xiiii. daye, lette thee blood of the right arme. And in the beginning of Aprill, the xi. daye, on the lefte arme. And in the end of May iii. or v. day, on whether arme thou wilte. And thus of all that yeare, thou ſhalte ſykerly be wariſh from the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and from the falling gowte, and from the fyſter gowte, and from loſſe of thy ſight.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bial mageſt in ſente loqui of Ptholomei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eche mans body is ruled by a certaine ſigne of the Zodyack.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:21"/>
            <p>Wherefore as ſayeth Ptholomens in the place of bone. If thou be ſycke in any limbe, doe no medicine vnto that lymbe, when the Moone is in the ſygne of that lymbe, for it ſhall rather hynder, then fourther. And namely flee blood letting, at that time of thoſe lymbes. Thus ſhalte thou knowe whiche ſygnes reigneth in whiche lymbes.</p>
            <p>The Bull reigneth in the neck and in the throate ouer all.</p>
            <p>The Gemuſe reigneth in the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, armes, and haudes.</p>
            <p>The Creues or Lobſter, reigneth in the breaſt ſtomacke, and limbes, arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, the mylte, heart, lyuer, and gall, and thoſe iii. be the ſignes of Ver.</p>
            <p>The Lyon reigneth in the backe, ſyde, bones, ſinewes, and griſtles.</p>
            <p>The Mayde reigneth in the wombe Myddryfe, and Guttes. And alſo ſhe reygneth, other whyle in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke,
<pb facs="tcp:22380:21"/>lyner, gall, and mylte, and other nut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſe limbes, beneath the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drife.</p>
            <p>And the Crab in the hearte, lunges, and arteries, and other ſmale lymbes, about the middryfe, and thoſe three ſignes are in Sommer.</p>
            <p>The Ballaunce reigneth in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and in the reignes, and the lower partes of the wombe.</p>
            <p>The Scorpyon reigneth in the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in the arſe, and in other preuy har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and in the maryes.</p>
            <p>The Sagittaries <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>neth in the thyes, and buttockes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and theſe three are ſignes of harueſt.</p>
            <p>The Caprycorne reygneth in the knees.</p>
            <p>The Aquarie reygneth in the legges and ancles.</p>
            <p>The Fyſhe reygneth in the Feete, and thoſe three be the ſygues of wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:22"/>
            <p>¶ Saturne, Iupſter, Mars, Soll, Venus, Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>y, and Lund.</p>
            <p>¶ Saturnus is cauſe of deth, dearth, and place.</p>
            <p>¶ Iupſter is muſe of long peace, reſt, and vertuous liuing.</p>
            <p>¶ Mars is cauſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s debate, and warre</p>
            <p>¶ Soll is cauſe of lyfe health, and waring.</p>
            <p>¶ Venus is cauſe of luſty loue, and Lechery.</p>
            <p>¶ Mercury is caiſe of much ſpeeche, Marchan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eightes.</p>
            <p>¶ Luna is cauſe of moyſtones greate waters and vyolent floudes.</p>
            <p>Saturne hower is good and ſtrong to doe all thinges that aſketh ſtrength onely, and to noughte elſe ſaue to bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle, for it is wonderous euill, that man or woman, that hath that ſtarre Saturne to hys plannet, he is melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colyous, black, and goeth ſwiftelye, he
<pb facs="tcp:22380:22"/>hath a voyde heart, wicked and bitter as wormewoode, he will lightlye be wroth, he is ian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ous, witty, couetous and yrerons, he eateth haſtely and is falſe, and moſt what louing to lye, and hath ſhining eyen as a Ent, he hath in the forehead a marke or a wounde, of fyre, he is poore, and his cloathes are rent vnto a tyme, and thus he hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſygnes and all his couetous is by other mens poſſeſſions, and not by bys owne.</p>
            <p>Iupiter hower is good in all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, namely to peace, loue and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde. Who that hath thys ſtarre to hys Planet, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>he is ſang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>, rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, and goeth a large pace, neyther to ſwifte, nor to ſofte, his ſtature is ſeemely, and ſhyninge hes hath a fayre vyſage, louelye ſemblaunce, fayre lyppes, fayre heares, and a ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning broade face, fayre b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>vies, hys cloathes are good and ſtronge,
<pb facs="tcp:22380:23"/>he is ſweete, peaceable, and ſofte.</p>
            <p>Mars hower is euill, and not full euill, it is better by night then by daye. For it is Maſculyne on the night, and Femynine on the daye. It is good to doe anye thing, but wyth greate ſtrength, by nighte it is good to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter battayle, and alſo by daye, but not ſo much good as by nighte. Who that hath this ſtarre to hys Planet, hys making is of good defence, and often tymes his face is red with blood, hys face is ſmall and ſotell, and laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, and he hath eyen as a Catte. And all the dayes of hys lyfe, he wyll accuſe many men of euill, hee hath a wounde of a ſworde in his face, he is moſte Colericke. And thus he hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſignes.</p>
            <p>¶ Soll hower is worſte of all other howres, no man in this hower maye do his will ſaue Kynges, and Lordes, and that wyth greate ſtrength. Who
<pb facs="tcp:22380:23"/>that in this hower entreth battayle: hee ſhall be deade there. Who that hath this ſtarre to his Planet. He hath ſharpe eyen, greate ſpeeche, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thoughtes in hys heart, he is wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and auarous, neyther whyte nor blacke, but betwixte both, hee hath a marke in the face or a wounde, and hath a wound in hys body of fyre, and he is right wicked and grudging in hys deedes.</p>
            <p>Venus hower is good in all thinges, and it is better on nyghte than on daye, euer till myddaye, at midday it is not good, for the ſunne couereth it. On Sunday the ix. hower is Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus hower, ſue not then to anye Lord ne poteſtate, for if thou doe thou ſhalte fynde him wrothe. Who that hath this ſtarre to his Planet, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye if he be borne by night in Venus hower, he is whyte and hath a rounde face, little foreheade, rounde beard,
<pb facs="tcp:22380:24"/>he hath a myddle noſe, and myddle heeres of eyen, he is laughing and len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigious, and he hath a marke in the face, hys making is fayre and playne, and oft tymes his nether lip is greater then the ouer. And who that is borne, vnder Venus, when ſhe is not in full power, he hath a ſharpe noſe and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what crooked, fayre heeres, ſofte eyen of running water, the is a ſinger, he longeth much of games, and loueth them well, and his tales he ſweete.</p>
            <p>Mercurious hower from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynninge to the middle, is good in all thinges, and from the middle to the ende it is harde, and it is not much better on nighte then on day, and eche tyme of the nighte and daye hee ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth before the Sunne or behynde, therefore hee hath hys power muche more by nighte then by daye, from morne to the fyfte hower of the day, he hath his power, and from thence to
<pb facs="tcp:22380:24"/>the nynth, he hath no power. Who that hath this ſtarre to hys planet, he hath a ſharpe ſtature, and a ſharpe long face, long eyen long noſe, great heeres of hys eyen, and thicke, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe forehead, long bearde, thynne heere, long armes, long fyngers, long feete, long hatrell of the heade, hee is meeke and loueable, and he will doe eche thing to certayne ſpace, hee is more whyte then blacke, and ofte tymes ryghte whyte, and hee hath greate ſhoulders. And who that is borne vnder Mercurious, when he is not in his full power.</p>
            <p>That is to ſaye. From the fyrſte hower of the daye, to the nynth, he is black and dry, he hath crowded teeth, and ſharpe, he hath a wound in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy wyth fyre, he is ſcorged wyth wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des or ſmitten wyth a ſword, and men ſayeth on him an euill name, of euill tales, and of manſlaughter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:25"/>
            <p>The Moones hower is ryght good and righte euill from the fourth day, to the xvii. it is good, namelye to all thoſe that are borne in it, and from the xvii. daye to the xx. daye, it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what good, but not ſo good: &amp; from the xx. day, to the xxvii. day it is euil, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to all thoſe that are borne in it. Who that hath this ſtar in his Planet and borne therevnder, when it is in full power, he hath a playne face, and pale, ſometyme lentigious, and doeth his willes to men, he hath ſomewhat ſeemely ſemblaunce, and he is ryche, he hath meane ſtature, neyther to long nor to ſhorte, he hath ſtrayghte lyppes, and hollowe eyen. Who that is borne vnder this ſtarre, when it is not in full power, he hath a ſtrayghte face and drye, and malicious, he hath little teeth, and Albugine, that is to ſaye. A whyte ſtrike in the eare.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:25"/>
            <head>¶ The nature and conditions which is found comprehended in man.</head>
            <list>
               <item>NAturally a man is hardye as the Lyon. i.</item>
               <item>Prue and worthy as the Oxe. ii.</item>
               <item>Large and liberall as the Cocke. iii.</item>
               <item>Auaricious as the Dogge. iiii.</item>
               <item>Hardy and ſwifte as the Harte. v.</item>
               <item>Debonayre and true as the Turtle Doue. vi.</item>
               <item>Malicious as the Leopard. vii.</item>
               <item>Pryue and tame as the Doue. viii.</item>
               <item>Dolorous and guilefull as the fox. ix.</item>
               <item>Simple and milde as the Lambe. x.</item>
               <item>Shrewde as the Ape. xi.</item>
               <item>Light as the Horſe. xii.</item>
               <item>Softe and pittifull as the Beare. xiii.</item>
               <item>¶ Deare and precyous as the Oly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant. xiiii.</item>
               <item>¶ Good and holeſome as the Vny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corne. xv.</item>
               <item>Vyle and ſlouthfull as the Aſſe. xvi:</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:22380:26"/>
               <item>Fayre and prowd as the Pecock. xvii.</item>
               <item>Glotonous as the Wolfe. xviii.</item>
               <item>Enuyous as a Bytch. xix.</item>
               <item>Rebell and inobediente as the Nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingale. xx.</item>
               <item>Humble as the Pigyon. xxi.</item>
               <item>Fell and fooliſh as the Ouſtrich. xxii.</item>
               <item>Profytable as the Pyſmyre. xxiii.</item>
               <item>Diſſolute and Vacabounde, as the Goate. xxiiii.</item>
               <item>Spitefull as the Pheſaunt. xxv.</item>
               <item>Softe and meeke as the Chiken. xxvi.</item>
               <item>Moueable and varying, as the Fyſhe. xxvii.</item>
               <item>Lecherous as the Bore. xxviii.</item>
               <item>Stronge and puiſſaunte, as the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell. xxix.</item>
               <item>Traytour as the Mule. xxx.</item>
               <item>Aduyſed as the Mouſe. xxxi.</item>
               <item>Reaſonable as an Aungell. xxxii.</item>
               <item>And therefore he is called the little world, or elſe he is called all creatures, for he doth take parte of all.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:26"/>
            <head>¶ Here followeth the diſcription of the fower Elementes, and of the iii. Complections.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Doe thee to wyt that in ech man &amp; woman reyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ech planet and euery ſigne of the Zodiack, and euery prime qualities, and euery Elemente, and euery complecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but not in euery lyke, for in ſome men reigneth one more, and in ſome reigneth another, and therefore men be of dyuers manners, wherfore good it is that we ſee ſhortely the kinde of thoſe primes qualityes, and ſo forth on the others.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ Of the foure Prime qualities and what they are.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:27"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oure Pryme qualityes there bee. That is to ſaye, moyſteneſſe, hote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, dryeneſſe, be two contraryes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the may not nigh together wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a meane, for the hotenes on the one ſide bindeth them together, &amp; coldneſſe on the other ſyde. Alſo hoteneſſe and coldeneſſe are two contraries, and therefore they maye not nighe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wythout a meane, for the moyſteneſſe on the one ſyde, byndeth them together. And dryeneſſe on the other, moyſtnes is cauſe of euery thick ſubſtaunce, and of euery ſweete taſte. And there agayne dryneſſe is cauſe of euery thin ſubſtaunce, &amp; of euery ſoure ſtinking taſte. And alſo hoteneſſe is cauſe of enery red coulour, and large quantitye. There agayne coldeneſſe is cauſe of euery whyte coloure and little
<pb facs="tcp:22380:27"/>quantitye.</p>
            <p>¶ Combyne. That is to ſaye knitte theſe fower Pryme qualityes, alter theſe iiii. combinacions, that is to ſay, knittinges, and then they will holde iiii. Elementes, that is to ſaye. The Ayre moyſt and hote. The Fyre hote and drye. The earth drye and colde. The Water colde and moyſte. The Ayre and the Earth, are two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traryes, and therefore they maye not nigh together, but as Fyre byndes them on the one ſide betweene them. And the water on the other ſyde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them. Alſo Fyre and Water, are two contraryes, and therefore they maye not nigh together, but as the Ayre betweene them byndes on the one ſyde. And the Earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene byndeth them together, on the otherſide. The Fyre is ſharp, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till, and moueable. The Ayre is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till, moueable, and corpulent, and dull.
<pb facs="tcp:22380:28"/>The Earth is corpulente and thycke. The Water is moueable, corpulente and dull. The Earthe is corpulente, dull, and vnmoueable, righte as an eggeſhell, Vingoſe a thinſkin. And that ſkin Vingoſe the whyte, and in the middeſte of the yolke, is a little tender hole, righte ſo the fyre Vyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goſe the Ayre, ten times more, and ten tymes. Then the Ayre Vyngoſe the Water ten tymes more, and ten tymes tymer then the Water, The water Vyngoſe the Earth ten tymes more, and ten tymes timer than the Earth. In the hearte of the Earthe is the Senter of the worlde. That is to ſaye, the middeſte poynte. And in euery Senter is hell. And there agayne aboute the Fyre, are the ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and aboute them is heauen Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalin, that is to ſaye, waters of all bliſſe, departed in ix. ordes of Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, then is Heauen in the higheſte
<pb facs="tcp:22380:28"/>rownes, and largeſt. And there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne is Hell in the loweſt, naroweſt, and ſtraighteſt.</p>
            <p>Right as there be iiii. Elementes, ſo there bee fower Complections, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in all manner qualityes, to theſe fower Elementes.</p>
            <p>The fyrſt is Sanguine, that is to ſay blood, gendreth in the lyuers, lymbe, and lyke to the Ayre.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is Choler, gendred in the Gall, and lyke thereto. And it is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Fyre.</p>
            <p>The thyrde is Melancholye, gende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the mylte, and lyke to the dreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of blood, and it accordeth to the Earth.</p>
            <p>The fourth is Flumes, gendered in the Lunges, lyke to galte, and it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordeth to the water. A Sanguyne man much may, and much coueyteth, for he is moyſt and hote.</p>
            <p>A Chollerycke man, muche co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyteth
<pb facs="tcp:22380:29"/>and little maye, for he is hote and drye.</p>
            <p>A Melancholious man, little may and little coueyteth, for he is drye and colde.</p>
            <p>A Flumaticke man, little couey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and little may, for he is colde and moyſt.</p>
            <p>A Sanguine man is large, louing, glade of cheare, laughinge, and rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye of cloure, ſtedfaſt, fleſhlye, ryghte hardye, mannerly, gentle, and well nouriſhed.</p>
            <p>A Choloricke man is guilefull, falſe and wrathfull, traytoures, and right hardy, quint, ſmall, drye, and black of coloure.</p>
            <p>A Melancholyous man, is enuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſorry, couetous, harde, and falſe, holdining, guilefull, dredfull, flothfull, and cleare of colour.</p>
            <p>A Flumaticke man is ſlomery, ſleepy, ſlowe, ſleightfull, and muche
<pb facs="tcp:22380:29"/>ſpetting, dull, and harde of wyt, fat vyſage, and white of coloure.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ Of the iiii. quarters of the yeare, and of the iiii. complections, and what they are.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the yeare bee foure quarters, ruled by theſe foure complections, that is to ſay. Ver, Sommer, Harueſt, and Wynter. Ver hath iii. moneths. That is to ſay, March, Aprill, and Maye. And it is ſanguine complection. Sommer hath alſo iii. monthes. That is to ſaye, Iune, Iuly, and Auguſt. And thys quarter is cholerick complection. Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt hath alſo iii. monthes, that is to ſay, September, October, Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and this quarter is Melancholius complection. Winter hath alſo iii.
<pb facs="tcp:22380:30"/>monthes. That is to ſaye, December, Ianuary, and February, &amp; thys quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is flumaticke complection.</p>
            <p>Eche day alſo theſe fower complecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons reigneth, that is to ſay, from three after midnight, vnto ix. reigneth ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine, and from ix. after midnighte, to three after midday, reigneth chollo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, and from iii. after middaye, to xi. after middaye reigneth Melancholy, and from ix. after midday, to iii. after midnight reigneth fleume.</p>
            <p>Alſo in the fower Quarters of the worlde reigneth theſe fower complec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. That is to ſaye, Sanguyne in the Eaſt. Chollericke in the South. Melancholy in the Weſt. And fleume in the North.</p>
            <p>Alſo the fower complections reyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in fower ages of man. That is to ſay. Choller in Childhode. Sanguine in manhood. Flume in age. And Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholius in old childhoode. If from
<pb facs="tcp:22380:30"/>the byrth, to xiiii. yeare full done, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode is from thence to xxx. yeare age. From thence to l. yeare. And olde from thence to lxxx. yeare, and ſo forth to death.</p>
            <p>Alſo theſe fower complections reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in fower partes of mans body.</p>
            <p>Choller reygneth in all the ſoulet lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, from the breaſt vpward.</p>
            <p>Sanguyne reigneth in all ſmall lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes. Alſo from the middrife to the we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand.</p>
            <p>And Flume reygneth in all noury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing limbes, alſo from the reynes to the middryfe.</p>
            <p>And Melancholy reygneth in all the limbes, from the reignes downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde.</p>
            <p>Wherefore euery mans vrine is caſt in fower, that is to ſaye, Corkill, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfice, Myddeſt, and grounde, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry partye of the vrine to hys parte of mans bodye. And therefore to fower
<pb facs="tcp:22380:31"/>thinges in euery vryne wee muſt take heede, that is to ſaye, Subſtaunce, quantitye, Choler, and contente, three Subſtaunces there are: That is to ſay, thicke, thin, and middle.</p>
            <p>Thicke Subſtaunce betokeneth much moyſtnes.</p>
            <p>Thinne ſubſtaunce betokeneth much drynes.</p>
            <p>And myddle ſubſtaunce betokeneth temporaunce.</p>
            <p>Alſo iii. Quantityes bee in Vryne. That is to ſaye, Much, Little, and Meane.</p>
            <p>Much quantitye betokeneth greate colde.</p>
            <p>And little quantity betokeneth great heate.</p>
            <p>And meane quantitye betokeneth temperaunce.</p>
            <p>Alſo take heede to the taſte whether it be ſweete or not.</p>
            <p>Sweete taſte betokeneth health.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:31"/>
            <p>And other taſte betokeneth ſycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>Alſo in Vrynes be xx. coloures, of the which the fyrſte ten betokeneth colde, and the other ten betokeneth heate.</p>
            <p>The x. coloures that betokeneth cold are theſe.</p>
            <p>The fyrſt is blacke, a darke cole and commeth of lyued going before.</p>
            <p>The ſeconde lyke to leade, and thoſe two betokeneth mortifycation.</p>
            <p>The thyrde is whyte as cleare wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>The fourthe is lacktike, lyke to whay.</p>
            <p>The fyfte is caropoſe, lyke to graye ruſſet, or to Camels heare.</p>
            <p>Thy ſixt is yelow lyke to ſalow leaues falling of trees, and thoſe iiii. coloures betokeneth indigeſtion.</p>
            <p>The ſeuenth is ſubpale, that is to ſay not full pale.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:32"/>
            <p>The eyght is pale, lyke to ſome ſodden fleſhe.</p>
            <p>The nynth is Subſitryne, that is to ſay, fulſitryne.</p>
            <p>The tenth is ſytryn, lyke to a pony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiter, or to right yelow flowers.</p>
            <p>And theſe fower coloures betokeneth beginning of digeſtion.</p>
            <p>Nowe we haue ſeene the coloures which betokeneth colde. So we will ſee the other ten whiche betokeneth heate.</p>
            <p>The fyrſt is Subrife, that is to ſay, not full ruffe.</p>
            <p>The ſeconde is ruffe, lyke to fyne Golde.</p>
            <p>And thoſe two coloures betokeneth perfecte digeſtion. So the vryne be middle of ſubſtaunce, myddle of quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, ſweete of taſte, and without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes.</p>
            <p>The thyrd is ſubrife, that is to ſay ful redde.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:32"/>
            <p>The fourth is redde, lyke Saffron durte.</p>
            <p>The fyfte is ſubrugund, that is to ſay not full rubugund.</p>
            <p>The ſyxte is rubygunde, lyke a ſtrong flame of fyre. And theſe fower coloures betokeneth paſſing of dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
            <p>The ſeuenth Ynopoſe, like to whyte wyne.</p>
            <p>the eyght is Kinanos, lyke to rotten blood. And theſe two betokeneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtyon.</p>
            <p>The ninth is greene, as the cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocke.</p>
            <p>The tenth is blacke, as a cleare blacke horne. And thys blacke com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of greene going to fore. And theſe two betokeneth aduſtion and death.</p>
            <p>In Vryne be eyghteene contentes. That is to ſaye, Serkell, Ampull, Graynes, Clowdes, Scume, At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer,
<pb facs="tcp:22380:33"/>Fatnes, Humer, Blood, Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, Heres, Scalos, Bran, Cryno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſe, Sperme, Duſt, Eſkes, Sedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, or Ipoſtas.</p>
            <p>The Serkle, ſheweth all the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lityes of the head.</p>
            <p>Ampull, that is to ſay creme, ſheweth alſo the brayne diſturbed.</p>
            <p>Graynes betoken of remne, and glutte.</p>
            <p>Clowdes ſheweth vyce, of the ſmall limbes.</p>
            <p>Scumme, that is to ſaye fome, ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth ventoſitye, and often the Iaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes.</p>
            <p>Atterer that is to ſay quiter, ſheweth vyce of the reygnes. The bladder, or of the lyuer.</p>
            <p>Fatneſſe as oyle droppes, ſheweth waſting and diſſolucion of the bodye, namely of the loynes.</p>
            <p>¶ Humer, lyke glet, or like dreſtes, of blood, or rotten Gall, it ſheweth
<pb facs="tcp:22380:33"/>vice of the middrife, or aboue or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath.</p>
            <p>Blood ſheweth vice of the liuer, or of the reignes, or of the bladder.</p>
            <p>Grauell ſheweth the ſtone.</p>
            <p>Heres ſheweth the diſſolution, of the fatnes of all the body, of the reignes namely.</p>
            <p>Scalos and branne, ſheweth the thirde ſpyce of Feueretyke iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <p>Sperme, that is to ſaye mankinde, ſheweth to much lechery. Duſt ſheweth the gowte, or a woman conceyued.</p>
            <p>Eſkes the preuye harneis to be gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>Zedymen, that is to ſay, clods in the grounde of the vryne, or breaking vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde</p>
            <p>The Cyrkle is called Ipoſtas. That is to ſaye, the grounde, and it hath moſte ſygnyfycation of all
<pb facs="tcp:22380:34"/>and namelye of the lower par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes.</p>
            <p>Of euery mans bodye, bee fower principall lymbes, that is to ſaye, ſoulet limbes, ſmall lymbes, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing limbes, and gendring lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes.</p>
            <p>Sowlet lymbes, be the braynes, and all that are there aboute, downe to the weſand.</p>
            <p>Small lymbes be the hearte, and the lunges, and all that be aboute them, betwixte the weſand and the middrife.</p>
            <p>Nouriſhing lymbes, be the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Mylte, Gall, and guttes, and all that be about them, betweene the Weſand and the Middryfe, and the Reygnes.</p>
            <p>Gendring lymbes, be the reygnes, bladder, preuie harneys, &amp; the lymbes about, fro the reygnes downwarde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:34"/>
            <head>¶ Alſo here followeth an A.B.C. Whereby thou mayeſt knowe of what Planet euery man is.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>E. <hi>1.</hi> I.S. <hi>1.</hi> B.K. <hi>2.</hi> Q.R. <hi>2.</hi> G.L. <hi>3.</hi> D.M. <hi>4.</hi> C.D. <hi>6.</hi> V. <hi>2.</hi> L. <hi>7.</hi> F. <hi>8.</hi> P. <hi>1.</hi> X. <hi>9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Departe this by <hi>9.</hi> vnto a hundred. And <hi>1.</hi> or <hi>8.</hi> be ouer, then the Sunne is hys Planet, if <hi>2.</hi> or <hi>9.</hi> be ouer, then Venus is hys Planet: If <hi>3.</hi> be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, then he is of Mercury: If <hi>4.</hi> be ouer then he is of the Moone: If <hi>5.</hi> be ouer, then he is of Saturnus: If <hi>6.</hi> be ouer, then hee is of Iupyter: If <hi>7.</hi> be ouer, then hee is of Mars.</p>
            <p>¶ Adam. <hi>31.</hi> Andren. <hi>12.</hi> Aldon. <hi>25.</hi> Nufos. <hi>12.</hi> Benaſter in is. <hi>92.</hi> Becus. <hi>9.</hi> Dauid. <hi>9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Alſo here followeth another A.B.C. to knowe by, of what ſygne in the Zody<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack euery man is, that is to ſay, vnder which ſygne he is borne, and to whyche ſygne he is moſte lyke. Alſo here by thou mayeſt knowe hys fortune, and the momente in the
<pb facs="tcp:22380:35"/>which he ſhall dye. Alſo here by thou maye knowe thy fortune, and infortune of manye thinges, Townes, Cities, and Caſtles.</p>
            <p>¶ A<hi>2.</hi> B<hi>2.</hi> C<hi>20.</hi> D<hi>41.</hi> E<hi>5.</hi> F<hi>24.</hi> G<hi>3.</hi> H<hi>20.</hi> I<hi>10.</hi> K<hi>13,</hi> L<hi>42.</hi> M<hi>12.</hi> N<hi>22.</hi> O<hi>21.</hi> P<hi>21.</hi> Q<hi>24.</hi> R<hi>27.</hi> S<hi>22.</hi> T<hi>91.</hi> V<hi>13</hi> X<hi>20.</hi> Y<hi>20.</hi> T<hi>7,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ If thou wylte knowe by thys A.B.C. anye man as it is ſayde before, take hys name and hys mothers name. And alſo if thou wilte knowe of anye Towne, by thys A.B.C. as it is ſayde before, then take that Townes name, and the name of the Cyttye of Ieruſalem, for that is the mother of all Townes, and then account the letters of the names, by the number of thys A.B.C. and when thou haſte all done, departe it by <hi>28.</hi> and if <hi>1.</hi> or <hi>2.</hi> be ouer, then that that thou ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt longeth to the Weather: and if <hi>3.</hi> or <hi>4.</hi> or <hi>5.</hi> be ouer, then that that thou ſéekeſt lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the Bull, and if <hi>6.</hi> or <hi>7.</hi> be ouer, then longeth it to the Iemuſe, and if <hi>8.</hi> or <hi>9.</hi> be ouer, then longeth it to the Crabe, and if <hi>10.11.</hi> or <hi>12.</hi> then longeth it to the Lyon, and if <hi>13.</hi> or <hi>14.</hi> then longeth it to the Virgine, and if <hi>15.</hi> or <hi>16.</hi> be ouer, then longeth it to the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and if <hi>17.18.</hi> or <hi>19.</hi> then longeth it to the Scorpyon, and if <hi>20.</hi> or <hi>21.</hi> then longeth it to the Sagitarie, and if <hi>22.</hi> or <hi>23.</hi> then lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth
<pb facs="tcp:22380:35"/>it to the Caprycorne, and if <hi>24.</hi> or <hi>25.</hi> then longeth it to the Aquary, and if <hi>26.27.</hi> or <hi>28.</hi> then longeth it to the Fyſhe.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Another Alphabet.</head>
               <p>DEparte anye thing in <hi>7.</hi> by the proper name of theſe letters: A. will tell, whiche of the <hi>7.</hi> it is, by the ouer number de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided by <hi>9.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>A.<hi>3.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B.<hi>4.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C.<hi>2.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D.<hi>2.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>E.<hi>2.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>F.<hi>4.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>G.<hi>2.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>H.<hi>5.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I.<hi>3.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>K.<hi>5.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>L.<hi>6.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>M.<hi>25.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>N.<hi>25.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>O.<hi>12.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>P.<hi>13.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Q.<hi>15.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>R.<hi>8.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S.<hi>13.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>T.<hi>2.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>V.<hi>23.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>X.<hi>98.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Y.<hi>56.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Z.<hi>34.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:36"/>
            <head>¶ To knowe the weather that ſhall bee all the yeare, after the chaunge of euerye Moone, by the Pryme dayes.</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vndaye Pryme, drye weather.</l>
            <l>Munday Pryme, moyſt weather.</l>
            <l>Tueſday Pryme, colde and wynde.</l>
            <l>Wedneſday Pryme, meruaylous.</l>
            <l>Thurſeday Pryme, fayre and clere.</l>
            <l>Fryday Pryme, fayre and fowle.</l>
            <l>Suturday Pryme, rayne.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ A Rule to knowe vppon what Letter, what hower, and what minute, as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:36"/>
            <p>Pryme vppon hora mynutes.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>29.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>9.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>B</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>4.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>5.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>C</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>13.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>1</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>D</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>20.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>18.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>E</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>18.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>12.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>F</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>21.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>4.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>G</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>13.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>20.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Vermore thus reigneth theſe feuen planets. Firſt reigneth Saturne, then Iupiter, then Mars, then Soll, then Venus, then Mercurye, and then Luna, Saturne
<pb facs="tcp:22380:37"/>is Lord on Saturday, Iupiter is lord on Thurſday, Mars is Lord of Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, Soll on Sunday, Venus on Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and Mercury of wedneſday, and Luna on Munday. Saturne Iupy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Mars, Soll, &amp; Mercury, is maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culine. That is to ſay Mankinde, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, and Luna, are Feminine, that is to ſay womankind. Saturne, Mars, and Luna, are euill Planets, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyter, ſoll, and Venus, be good Planettes, and Mercury is chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable.</p>
            <p>On Saturdaye the fyrſte hower after midnighte reygneth Saturne, the ſeconde hower Iupiter, the third hower Mars, the iiii. hower Soll, the v. hower Venus, the ſince hower Mercury, the vii. hower Luna. And then againe Saturne the viii. hower, and Iupiter the ix. hower, Mars the x. hower, Soll the xi. hower, Venus the xii. hower, Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye
<pb facs="tcp:22380:37"/>the xiii. hower, and Luna the xiiii. hower. Then agayne the thyrde of day time. Saturne the xv. hower, Iupyter the xvi. hower, Mars the xvii. hower, foll the xviii. hower, Venus the xix. hower, Mercury the xx. hower, and Luna the xxi. hower. And then agayne the iiii. tyme, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne the xxii. hower, Iupyter the xxiii. hower, Mars the xxiiii. hower. And then beginneth ſoll, in the hower after midnighte on the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, Venus the ſecond hower, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury the thirde hower, Luna the iiii. hower, ſaturne the fyfte hower. And ſo forth hower by hower, and Planet by Planet, in order as they ſtande. Eche Planet to hys owne daye, reyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth euermore certaynely, the tyrſte hower, the viii. hower, the xv. hower, and the xxii. hower. And ſo fourth euermore one after another. And nexte after that reygneth the Planet
<pb facs="tcp:22380:38"/>that is nexte in order, as thus, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, Iupyter, Mars, Soll, Venus, Mercurius, and Luna.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ Of the moſte beſt and profytableſſe dayes that be in the yeare, to let blood.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning of March that is to ſaye, the vi. and the tenth daye thou ſhalte drawe out blood of the right arme.</p>
            <p>In the beginninge of Aprill, of the lefte arme, and that in the xi. daye, for the ſight. In the ende of Maye, of which arme thou wylte, and that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne the Feuer, and if thou ſo doeſt, neyther thou ſhalte loſe thy ſighte, nor thou ſhalte haue no Feuers, how long thou lyueſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:38"/>
            <p>¶ <hi>Quot retinente vita et non mortis Imago Si ſemperfuerint viuens morietur et infra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Goodhap.</cell>
                     <cell>Miſhap.</cell>
                     <cell>Miſhap.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="4">Beſt.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>1.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>13.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell rows="4">Sorrowe.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>2.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>14.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>24.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>3.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>16.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>26.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>4.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>17.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>23.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="3">Beſt.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>6.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>18.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>27.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="3">Dearth.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>11.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>8.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>10.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>20.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Eſt veſper Eplaton deampulle. Philoſophie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="3">Vita.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>5.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>19.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell rows="3">Heauines.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>7.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>21.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>28.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>9.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>22.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>29.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2">Vita.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>12.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>25.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>30.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="2">Ioye.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>15.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Vita.</cell>
                     <cell>Ioye.</cell>
                     <cell>Ioye.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Collige per numeroes aliquid cupis eſſe phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre Iunge ſimullatum feriaque Diem.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:39"/>
            <list>
               <item>A. iii.</item>
               <item>B. vi.</item>
               <item>C. xii</item>
               <item>D. xx.</item>
               <item>E. xxvi.</item>
               <item>F. xxv.</item>
               <item>G. iii.</item>
               <item>K. xv.</item>
               <item>L. xxi.</item>
               <item>M. xv.</item>
               <item>N. xxii.</item>
               <item>O. xx.</item>
               <item>P. xiiii.</item>
               <item>Q. xvi.</item>
               <item>R. iiii.</item>
               <item>S. xxix.</item>
               <item>T. xxviii.</item>
               <item>V. iiii.</item>
               <item>X. vi.</item>
               <item>Y. vi.</item>
               <item>Z. iii.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>Sunday. xiii.</item>
               <item>Munday. xviii.</item>
               <item>Thueſday. xv.</item>
               <item>Wedneſday. xxv.</item>
               <item>Thurſeday. xi.</item>
               <item>Fryday. xv.</item>
               <item>Saturday. xxvi.</item>
            </list>
            <p>¶ Thus endeth the Speare of Platon.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:22380:39"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho ſo euer in the vii. daye of Marche letteth him blood in the righte arme, in the leuenth daye of Aprill in the left arme, he ſhall not loſe the ſight of his eyen.</p>
               <p>And in the fower or fyfte laſt daye of Maye, in both armes be letten blood, he ſhal haue no feuers.</p>
               <p>Whoſoeuer in the fyrſte day of each moneth falleth into anye infyrmitye, the thyrd day enſuing is to dred, which if he paſſe, he ſhall eſcape tyll thirtye dayes.</p>
               <p>Who ſo falleth in the ſeconde day, is to dread which if he paſſe, though he long be ſick, he ſhalbe deliuered.</p>
               <p>He that falleth in the thirde daye, at nexte ſhalbe deliuered.</p>
               <p>He that falleth ſycke in the iiii. daye, he ſhall bee greeuouſlye to the xxviii. daye, whiche if hee paſſe, he ſhall eſcape.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22380:40"/>
               <p>He that falleth the fyft daye, thoughe he ſuffer greeuouſly, he ſhall eſcape.</p>
               <p>He that falleth in the ſixte day, though he ſeeme to be healde, neuer the latter in the fyfte daye of the other moone, he ſhall be deade.</p>
               <p>He that falleth in the vii. daye, wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out griefe he ſhall be delyuered.</p>
               <p>He that falleth the viii. daye, if he be not whole at the xii. daye, he ſhall be deade.</p>
               <p>He that falleth in the ninth daye, though it be wyth great griefe, he ſhal eſcape.</p>
               <p>He that falleth in the x. day, wythout doubt he ſhall be deade.</p>
               <p>He that falleth in the xi. daye, he ſhall be delyuered the next day.</p>
               <p>He that falleth in the xii. daye, but if he be delyuered wythin two dayes, within xv. he ſhall be deade.</p>
               <p>He that falleth in the xiii. daye, tyll the xviii. dayes he ſhall be ſycke, which
<pb facs="tcp:22380:40"/>if he paſſe, he ſhall eſcape.</p>
               <p>He that falleth in the fourteen daye he ſhall dwell till the xv. and ſo he ſhall eſcape.</p>
               <p>He that waxeth ſycke the xv. daye, but if he recouer wythin xviii. dayes, he ſhall be dead.</p>
               <p>He that falleth in the xvi. daye, though he be greeued till xxiiii. dayes, till the xxviii. dayes he ſhall eſcape.</p>
               <p>He that falleth in the xvii. day, he ſhall dye the x. day.</p>
               <p>He that falleth ſick in the xviii. daye, ſoone ſhall bee healed.</p>
               <p>He that falleth in the xix. daye, alſo ſhall eſcape.</p>
               <p>He that falleth ſyck in the xx. daye, in the v. daye he ſhall eſcape, but neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, in the moneth following he ſhalbe dead.</p>
               <p>He that waxeth ſycke in the xxi. day, but he runne into perrill of death within x. dayes of that other moneth,
<pb facs="tcp:22380:41"/>he ſhall be delyuered</p>
               <p>He that waxeth ſicke in the xxii. daye, but he runne into perill of death with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ten dayes of that other moneth, he ſhall be delyuered.</p>
               <p>He that falleth in the xxiii. daye, thoughe it be wyth greeuouſneſſe of payne, in the other moneth, he ſhall bee delyuered.</p>
               <p>He that falleth in the xxiiii. daye, in the xxvii. daye he ſhall bee delyuered, but neuertheleſſe in the moneth follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing he ſhall be dead.</p>
               <p>He that falleth ſycke in the xxv. day, thoughe he ſuffer a little, neuertheleſſe he ſhall eſcape.</p>
               <p>Hee that falleth in the xxvi. daye, thoughe he ſuffer to the outpaſſing, neuertheleſſe in that other moneth, he ſhall be delyuered.</p>
               <p>Hee that falleth in the xxvii. daye, it manaſſeth death.</p>
               <p>He that falleth in the xxviii. daye,
<pb facs="tcp:22380:41"/>it manaſſeth death.</p>
               <p>He that falleth the xxix. daye, little and little in that other month, he ſhall be deliuered.</p>
               <p>He that falleth ſicke in the xxx. daye, it is doubte whether hee paſſe anye of theſe.</p>
               <p>Alſo he that waxeth ſicke in the xxxi. whether hee ſhall eſcape, it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ Here followeth the nature of the xii. Signes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ries is hote and drye, nature of the fire, and gouerneth the heade &amp; face of man, &amp; is good for bleeding, when the Moone is in it, ſaue in the party that it gouerneth and ruleth Taurus is euill for bleeding.</p>
            <p>Taurus is drye and colde, nature of earth and gouerneth the necke and
<pb facs="tcp:22380:42"/>the knot vnder the throate, and is euill for bleeding.</p>
            <p>¶ Gemini is euill for bleeding.</p>
            <p>Gemini is hote and moyſt, nature of the ayre, and gouerneth the ſhoulders, the armes, the handes, and is euill for bleeding.</p>
            <p>¶ Cancer is indifferent for bleeding.</p>
            <p>Cancer is colde and moyſt, nature of water, and gouerneth the breaſt, the ſtomacke and the milte, and is indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, neyther to good nor to badde for letting of blood.</p>
            <p>¶ Leo is euill for bleeding.</p>
            <p>Leo is hote and drye, nature of fyre, and gouerneth the back and the ſides, and is euill for blood letting.</p>
            <p>¶ Virgo is indifferent for bleeding.</p>
            <p>Virgo is colde and drye, and nature of the earth, &amp; gouerneth the wombe, and the inwarde parties, and is ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good, nor euil for bleeding, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene both.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:42"/>
            <p>¶ Libra is right good for bleeding.</p>
            <p>Libra is hote and moyſte, nature of the ayre, and gouerneth the nauill, the reynes, and the lowe partes of the wombe, and is very good for bleeding.</p>
            <p>¶ Scorpio is indifferent for bleeding</p>
            <p>Scorpio is colde and moyſt, nature of the water, and gouerneth the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of man, and is neyther good nor bad for bleeding, but indifferente, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene both.</p>
            <p>¶ Sagittarius is good for bleeding.</p>
            <p>Sagittarius is hote and drye, nature of fire, and gouerneth the thighes and is good for bleeding.</p>
            <p>¶ Capricornus is euill for bleeding.</p>
            <p>Capricornus is colde and dry, nature of earth, and gouerneth the knees, and is euill for bleeding.</p>
            <p>¶ Aquarius is indifferent for bleding.</p>
            <p>Aquarius is hote and moyſte, nature of ayre, and gouerneth the legges and is neyther good nor euill for bleeding<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:22380:43"/>Piſces is indifferente for bleeding. Piſces is colde &amp; moyſt nature of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and gouerneth the feete, and is neyther good nor euill for bleeding, but indifferent.</p>
            <p>No man ought not to make inciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on nor touch wyth yron the members gouerned of any ſigne, the day that the Moone is in it, for feare of the greate effuſyon of blood that mighte happen: Nor in likewiſe when the ſunne is in it for the great daungers and perrill that might follow thereof.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ Here followeth the Anathomye of the bones in mans body, and the number of them, which is in all ii .C. and xlviii.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the top of the head is a bon that couereth the brayne, the which Ptholomeus calleth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Capitall bone. In the ſcull be two bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which bene called parietalls, that
<pb facs="tcp:22380:43"/>holdeth the brayne cloſe and ſtedfaſt. And more lower in the brayne, is a bone called the crowne of the heade, and one the one ſyde and on the other, bene two holes wythin the whyche is the pallays or roofe bone. In the part behynde the head bene iiii. lyke bones, to the which the chayne of the necke holdeth. In the noſe ben ii. bones. The bones of the chaftes aboue be xi. and of the neyther iaw ben ii. aboue the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite of the brayne, there is one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hynde named collaterall. The bones of the teeth be xxx. eyght, before iiii. aboue, &amp; iiii. vnderneth, ſharpe edged for to cut the morſels, and there is iiii. ſharpe ii. aboue, and ii. vnderneth, and ben called conines, for they be lyke co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies teeth. After that bene xvi. that be as they were homers or grindinge teeth, for they chewe and grynde the meate the whiche is eaten and there is iiii. aboue on euery ſyde, &amp; iiii. vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neath.
<pb facs="tcp:22380:44"/>And then the iiii. teeth of ſapy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on euery ſyde of the chaftes, one aboue and one vnderneath. In the chin from the head downewarde bene xxx. bones called knottes or ioyntes. In the breaſt before bene vii. bones, and on euerye ſyde xii. rybbes. By the necke betweene the head and the Shoulders, bene ii. bones named the ſheres, and ben the ii. ſhoulder blades. From the Shoulder to the Elboe, in ech arme is a bone called the Adiutor, from the Elbow to the hande bone, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery arme ben ii. bones, that ben called Cannes, in eche hand bene viii. bones, aboue the palme bene iiii. bones which bene called the Combe of the hande. The bones in the fingers in ech hande xv. in euery finger three. At the ende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ridge ben the huckle bones, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bene faſtened the two bones of the thighes, in eche knee is a bone called the knee plate.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:44"/>
            <p>From the knee to the foote in eche leg, ben ii. bones called canes or marybo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. In each foote is a bone called the ancle orpin of the foote, behynde the ancle is the heele bone in ech foote, the which is the loweſt parte of a man. And aboue each foote is a bone called the hallowe bone. In the plant of ech foote bene fower bones. Then ben the combes of the feete in ech of the which ben fyue bones, the bones in the toes in each foote bene the number of xiiii. Two bones ben before the belly, for to holde it ſtedfaſt with the two bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Two bones ben in the head be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the eares, cald oculares, we reken not the tender bones of the ende of the ſhoulders, nor of the ſydes, nor dyuers little griſtles and ſpeldres of bones for they be comprehended in the number aforeſayde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:45"/>
            <head>¶ Here followeth the Flubothomy, wyth the names of the vaynes, and where they reſt, &amp; how they ought to be letten blood.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere I do you to wit, that the vayne in the middeſt of the foreheade would be letten blood for the ach, &amp; payne of the heade, and for Feuers (Lytargy) and for the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grime in the head.</p>
            <p>About the two eares behinde is two vaynes the which be let blood to geue cleare vnderſtanding, and vertue of light hering, &amp; for thick breath, and for doubt of Meſelrye or Leprye. In the temple bene two vaynes, caled the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers for that they beat, which ben let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten blood, for to diminiſh and take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the greate replection and aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of blood that is in the brayne, that might noy the head and the eyen,
<pb facs="tcp:22380:45"/>and it is good agaynſt the gowte, the megrime, and dyuers other accidents that may come to the head.</p>
            <p>Vnder the tonge bene ii. vaynes, that ben letten blood for a ſicknes caled the Sequamy, and againſt the ſwelling &amp; apoſtumes of the throate, and agaynſt the Equinancye, by the which a man might dye ſodaynly for default of ſuch bleeding.</p>
            <p>In the neck ben ii. vaynes caled origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, for that they haue the courſe and abundaunce of all the blood that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneth the body of man, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally the head, but they ought not to be letten blood wythout the counſayle of the Phiſition, and thys bleeding auai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth much to the ſyckneſſe of Leprye, when it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth principally of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blood. The vayne of the hearte, taken in the arme profyteth to take away humors, or euill blood that might hurte the cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the heart, or the aperteinance, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:22380:46"/>is good for them that ſpitteth blood, &amp; that ben ſhorte winded, by the which a man may dye ſodaynely for defaulte of ſuch bleeding.</p>
            <p>The vayne of the liuer taken in the arme ſwageth the greate heate of the body of man, and holdeth the body in health, and this bleeding is profytable, alſo agaynſt the yelow axes, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtume of the liuer, and agaynſt the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, whereof a man may dye for default of ſuch bleeding.</p>
            <p>Betweene the maiſter finger and the leth finger to let blood, holpen the dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors that commeth in the ſtomack, and ſydes, as botches, and apoſtumes, and diuers other accedents that may come to theſe places, by great abundance of blood and humoures.</p>
            <p>In the ſydes betweene the wombe and the braunch, bene two vaynes of the which that of the right ſyde is let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten blood for the dropſy, and that of the
<pb facs="tcp:22380:46"/>lefte ſide for euery ſicknes that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth about the milte, and they ſhould bleede after the perſons be fat or leane, take good heede at foure fyngers nighe the inſicion, and they ought not to make ſuch bleeding, wythout the counſaile of the Phiſition.</p>
            <p>In euery foote bene three vaynes, of the which three, one is vnder the ancle of the foote named ſophan, the whiche is letten blood for to ſwage &amp; put oute dyuers humours, as botches and apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumes that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth about the groines and it profiteth much to women for to cauſe their menſtruoſity to deſcend, &amp; delaye the Emerodes that commeth in the ſecret places and other lyke.</p>
            <p>Betweene the wreſtes of the foote, and the great toe is a vayne the which is letten blood for dyuers ſickeneſſes, &amp; inconueniences, as the peſtilence that taketh a perſon ſodaynely, by the great ſuperabundance of humoures, &amp; thys
<pb facs="tcp:22380:47"/>bleding muſt be made wythin a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall daye, that is to ſay, wythin xxiiii. howers after that the ſyckneſſe is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the pacient, and before that the Feuer come on him, and this bleeding oughte to be done after the corpolence of the pacient.</p>
            <p>In the angles of the eyen, bene two vaynes, the which bene letten blood, for the rednes of the eyen, or watry or that runneth continually, and for dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other ſickneſſes that may happen and come by ouer greate abundaunce of humoures and blood.</p>
            <p>In the vayne of the ende of the noſe, is made a bleeding, the which is good for a red pympled face, as bene redde drops, puſtuls, ſmall ſcabs, and other infections of the heart, that may come therein by to great replection, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundaunce of bloud and humoures, &amp; it auayleth much agaynſt pympeled noſes, and other like ſickneſſes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:47"/>
            <p>In the mouth in the gummes ben iiii. vaynes, that is to ſay, two aboue and two beneth, the which ben leten blood for chaufing and canker in the mouth and for toothack.</p>
            <p>Betweene the lip and the chin is a vayne that is letten blood to geue a mendement vnto them that haue an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill breath.</p>
            <p>In ech arme bene iiii. vaynes, of the which the vayne of the head is the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, the ſecond next is from the hearte, the thyrd is of the liuer, and the fourth is from the mylte, otherwiſe called the low liuer vayne.</p>
            <p>The vayne of the head taken in the arme, ought to bleed for to take awaye the greate replection and aboundance of blood that may annoy the head, the eyen and the brayne, and auayleth greatly for chaungeable heates, and ſwelling faces and red, and for diuers other ſyckneſſes that maye fall and
<pb facs="tcp:22380:48"/>come by great abundaunce of blood.</p>
            <p>The vayne of the mylte, otherwyſe called the lowe vayne, ſhould bleed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt feuer tercians and quartaynes, and in it ought to be made a wide and a leſſe deepe wound then in any other vayne, for feare of winde, that it maye gather, and for a more incenuenience, for feare of a ſmowe that is vnder it, that is called the Leſard.</p>
            <p>In eche hande bene three vaynes, whereof that aboue the thombe ought to bleede, to take away the great hete of the viſage, and for much thick blood and humors that ben in the head, and thys vayne delayeth more then that of the arme.</p>
            <p>Betweene the little fynger, and the leche fynger, is letting of blood that greatly auayleth agaynſt all feuer ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, and quartaynes, and agaynſte flumes and diuers other lettinges that commeth to the paps and the milte.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:48"/>
            <p>In the thigh is a vayne, of the whych bleeding auayleth agaynſt doloure of the genitoures, and for to put out of mans dody humoures that bene in the graynes.</p>
            <p>The vayne that is vnder the ancle of the foote without is named Sciot, of the which bleeding is much worth agaynſt the paynes of the flancks, and for to make auoyde and iſſue diuers humoures which would gather in the ſayde place, and it auayleth greatly to women to reſtrayn their menſtruoſity when they haue to great abundance.</p>
            <p>¶ Thus endeth the Flubothomye.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <p>BE it to vnderſtande, that there be in the yeare fower Quarters, the which be named thus, Vere, Hyems, Eſtas, and Autumnus. Theſe ben the fower ſeaſons in the yeare, as Pryme tyme is the ſpring of the yeare, as Februarye, March, and Aprill. In
<pb facs="tcp:22380:49"/>theſe three months euery greene thing growing, begynneth to budde and flooriſhe.</p>
               <p>Then commeth ſommer, as Maye, Iune, and Iuly, and theſe three mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes euery herbe, grayne, and tree, is in his kinde, &amp; in hys moſt ſtrength, and beauty, and then the ſunne is at the higheſt.</p>
               <p>Then commeth Autumne, as Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, September and Detober, that al theſe fruites waxen rype, and bene ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and houſed.</p>
               <p>Then commeth nouember, Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and Ianuarie, and theſe three mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes be in the winter, that time the ſunne is at the loweſt, and is at the tyme of little profite, as we Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers ſaye, that the age of man is lxxii. yere, and that we lyken but one whole yere, for euermore we take ſyxe yeare for euery moneth, as Ianuary, or Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruarye, and ſo forth. For as the yeare
<pb facs="tcp:22380:49"/>chaungeth by the xii. monthes into xii. diuers manners.</p>
               <p>So doeth man chaunge hymſelfe xii. tymes in his lyfe by xii. ages, and euery vi. times vi. maketh xxxvi. And than man is at the beſt, and alſo at the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and xii. times vi. maketh lxxii. and that is the age of man.</p>
               <p>Thus muſt you counte and recken for euery month vi. yeare, or elſe it may be vnderſtand by the foure quarters, and ſeaſons of the yeare, ſo man is deuided into foure parts, as to youth, ſtrength, wyſedome, and age. He ſo to bee xviii. yeare yong, xviii. yeare ſtrong, xviii. yeare in wiſedome, and the fourth xviii. yere to goe to the ful age of lxxii.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:50"/>
            <head>¶ Here followeth to ſhow howe a man chaungeth xii. times, euen as the xii. months doeth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E muſt take the firſt vi. yeare for Ianuary, the which is of no vertue nor ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, in that ſeaſon nothing on the earth groweth. So man after that hee is borne, till he be vi. yeare of age, is wyth little or no witte, ſtrength, or cunning, and maye doe little or nothing that commeth to any profite.</p>
            <p>Then commeth February, and then the dayes longeth, and the ſunne is more hotter, then the fyeldes begin to waxe greene. So the other vi. yere till he come to xii. the childe beginneth to grow bigger, and is apt to learne ſuch thinges as is taught him.</p>
            <p>Then commeth the month of March, in which the labourour ſoweth the earth and planteth trees, and edyfieth
<pb facs="tcp:22380:50"/>houſes, the chylde in theſe vi. yeares waxeth big to learne Doctrine, and ſcience, and to be fayre and pleaſaunte and louing, for then he is xviii. yeares of age.</p>
            <p>Then commeth Aprill, that the earth and the trees is couered wyth greene Flowers. And in euery party goodes encreaſeth abundauntly. Then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the younge man to gather the ſweete flowers of hardineſſe, but then beware that the colde wyndes, and ſtormes of vices beate not downe the flowers of good maners, that ſhoulde bring man to honoure, for then is he xxiiii. yeare of age.</p>
            <p>Then commeth Maye, that is both fayre and pleaſaunte, for then Byrdes ſing in woodes and Foreſtes, nyght and daye, the ſunne ſhyneth hote, as then man is moſt luſty, mighty, and of deliuer ſtrength, and ſeeketh playes, ſportes, and manly paſtimes, for then
<pb facs="tcp:22380:51"/>is he full xxx. yeares of age.</p>
            <p>Then commeth Iune, and then is the ſunne at the higheſt in his meridional, he may aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d no higher in his ſtacion. Hys gleamering golden Beames ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the Corne, and then man is xxxvi. yeare, he maye aſcende no more, for then nature hath giuen them courage and ſtrength at the full, and ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the ſeedes of perfecte vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>Then commeth Iuly, that our fruites be ſet on ſunning, and our corne a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dening, but then the ſunne beginneth a little to deſcende downwarde. So then man goeth from youth towarde age, and beginneth for to acquainte him whyth ſadneſſe, for then he is come to xlii. yeare.</p>
            <p>After that then commeth Auguſt, then we gather in our corne, and alſo the fruites of the earth, And then man doeth hys dillygence to gather for to
<pb facs="tcp:22380:51"/>fynde hym ſelfe, to mayntayne hys wyfe, chyldren and hys houſholde, when age commeth on him, and then after that vi. yeare, he is xiviii. yeare of age.</p>
            <p>Then commeth September, that wynes be made, and the fruites of the trees be gathered: And then there wythall he doeth freſhly begin to gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe hys houſe, and make prouiſion of needefull things, for to lyue wyth in wynter, whych draweth verye neare, and then man is in his moſte ſtedfaſte and couetous eſtate, proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in wiſedome, purpoſing to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and keepe as much as ſhoulde bee ſufficient for him in hys age, when he maye gather no more, and then is hee liiii. yeare of age.</p>
            <p>And then commeth October, that all is into the aforeſayde houſe ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, both corne, and alſo other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:22380:52"/>of fruites, and alſo the laborers plowe and ſow new ſeedes on the erth for the yeare to come. And then he that nought ſoweth, nought gathereth, and then in theſe vi. yeare a man ſhall take himſelfe vnto God, for to do penance &amp; good workes, and then the benefites the yere after his death, he may gather and haue ſpirituall profyte, and then man is fully the tearme of lx. yeares.</p>
            <p>Then commeth Nouember, that the dayes be very ſhort, and the ſunne in manner giueth but little heate, and the trees loſen their leaues. The fields that were greene, looketh hoare, and gray. Then al manner of hearbes bene hyd in the ground, and then appeareth no flowers, and then wynter is come, that the man hath vnderſtanding of age, and hath loſt hys kindly hete and ſtrength, hys teeth begin to rotee and to fayle hym. And then hath he little hope of long lyfe, but deſyreth to come
<pb facs="tcp:22380:52"/>to the lyfe euerlaſting, and theſe vi. yeares maketh him lxvi. yeare of age. Then laſt commeth December, full of colde, wyth froſts, and ſnows, with great wyndes, and ſtormy weathers, that a man may not labor, nor nought doe. The ſunne is then at the loweſt, that it maye deſcende. Then the trees and the earth be hid in ſnowe, then it is good to hold them nie the fyre, and to ſpende the goodes that they gate in ſommer. For then man beginneth to waxe crooked and feeble, coughing &amp; ſpitting and loathſome, and then he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth hys perfecte vnderſtanding, and his heyres deſyre hys death. And theſe vi. yeare maketh him full lxxii. yeares, and if he lyue any longer, it is by his good guiding and dieting in hys youth howbeit, it is poſſible that a man may liue till he be a C. yeare of age, but ther be but few that liueth ſo long, tyll they come to a hundred yere of age.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:53"/>
            <head>¶ Hereafter followeth the Rutter of the diſtaunces from one Porte or countrey to another, and fyrſt of the compaſſe of England.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Compaſſe of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande rounde aboute, is iiii. M. iii. C. &amp; ix. myles. Venis doeth ſtande from Flaunders Eaſt and by South viii. C. myles.</p>
            <p>And nexte courſe by the ſea, from Flaunders to Iaffe, (is thys.) From Sluſe to Calays is lxx. miles. From Calays to Buchefe lxxx. myles. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Bucheffe to Lezard ii. C. lx. miles. From Lezard to Capfeneſtes, ſixe hundred l. miles. From Capfeneſter to Liſbone, is two hundred and lxxx. miles. From Liſbone to Cap S. Vincente
<pb facs="tcp:22380:53"/>to the ſtractes two C. xl. miles. From the ſtractes the Iebalter, vnto the Ile of Sardine xi. C. miles. From Malfitana in Sardine, to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalta, is iiii. C. and lx. myles. From Inalta by the courſe of Saro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gora and Sicill, to ſayle to Iaffe in Surrye, is a M. viii. C. miles. From Iaffe to Baffe in Sypre, to the Caſtle Roge, is ii. C. xx. miles. From Caſtle Roge to Rodes, a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. miles. From Rodes to Candy ii. C. l. myles. From Candy to Modon, three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred myles. From Modon to Corſue, three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred myles. From Corſu to Venis, is eyght hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred myles.</p>
            <p>THE length of the coſtes of Surry, of the Sea coſtes, is from the gulfe of Ermony, to the gulfe Dalarlze,
<pb facs="tcp:22380:54"/>nexte the South and bee Weſt, from Lazarya to Ryſe, is three ſcore and fyue miles. That is to vnderſtande, from Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in Ermony to Soldin, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth from the ryuer comming from Anthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oche lxx. miles.</p>
            <p>AND from Soldin, to the Porte of Lycha, nexte vnto the South fyftye miles. From Lycha to the Porte of Tortoſa South l. myles. From Tortoſa vnto the Porte Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poll ſouth l. myles. From Bernet to Acres ſouth, and bee weſt lxx. myles. From Acres to Porte Iaf, ſouth, and be weſt lxx. miles. From Porte Iaf, to Porte Delezara, ſouth, ſouth weſt a C. xxx. myles. From Damyat Lariza in Surrye, to Damiat in Egipt C. lxxx. miles.
<pb facs="tcp:22380:54"/>From Damyat to Babylon Alchare, lxxx. miles. From Damyat to Alexandre, a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred x. miles.</p>
            <p>THe length of Mare Maior is from the Gulfe S. George in the middeſt of the gulfe that is betwixt Trapaſant Sanaſtopoly to the porte of Meſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre weſt, from S. George a thouſand lx. miles. The bredth of the weſt ende, is from the bras S. George of Conſtantinople, vpon the ryuer of Danabes nexte the North, from S. George Braſe, fyue hundred lx. myles.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom Pero to Caffa, in Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, Northeaſt vi. C. myles. From Caffa to the ſtractes, of the Tane, Northeaſt, a hundred miles. The Gulfe of Tane is aboute ſixe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred myles.
<pb facs="tcp:22380:55"/>The Capt of Caffa is aboute ſixe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred myles. From the Head of Tane to Sanaſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poly, foure C. myles. From Sanoſtopoly, to Trapaſonde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by Weſt ii. C. l. myles. From Trapaſonde to Synopya, next<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the ſouth iiii. C. xxx. miles. From Synopya to Pero, nexte the Weſt, ſouthweſt ii. C. xxx. miles. From Pero to Meſſember, nexte the Norweſt ii. C. xxx. miles. From Meſſember to Mancro, North, Northeaſt, a C. ix. miles. From Mancro Caſtro, to Danobia, Northeaſt a C. xxx. miles. From Danobia to the ſtractes of Caf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fa nexte the Eaſt. ii. C. myles.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ The compaſſe of the Ilandes.</head>
            <p>THE Ile of Sypre, is aboute fyue hundred myles.
<pb facs="tcp:22380:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>The Iles of Roobes, is boute an C. xxx. myles. The Ile of Lange is aboute foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>core myles. The Ile of Necrypont, is about three hundred myles. The Ile of Cecilya, is aboute ſeuen hundred myles. The Ile of Sardyne, is about ſeuen hundred myles. The Ile of Mayorke, is aboute two hundred myles. The Ile of great Brytayne, is aboute two thouſand myles. The Ile of Irelande is aboute a M. vii. C. myles. The principallitye of Murre, is about vii. C. myles.</p>
            <trailer>¶ Thus endeth the Rutter of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce from one Porte or Countrye to another.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:56"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:57"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Jmprinted at London, in</hi> Fleeteſtreete, beneath the Conduit, at the Signe of S. Iohn Euangeliſt, by Hugh Iackſon. 1585.</p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22380:57"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
